Inventory of the World Without War Council records
Hoover Institution Archives
World without War Council records
1940-2011
84029
Hoover Institution Archives
250 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 cardfile box, 265 cubic foot boxes (372.5 linear feet)
Minutes, resolutions, correspondence, memoranda, reports, financial records, serial issues, bulletins, newsletters, and other printed matter, relating to peace movements in the United States, pacifism, conscientious objectors, disarmament, nuclear weapons, American foreign policy, world affairs, and the Vietnamese War.
Access
Boxes 1 to 508 may not be used without permission of the archivist. The remainder of the collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1984.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
The World Without War Council was a private, nonprofit American organization to promote peace.
In 1958, Robert Pickus founded Acts of Peace. In 1961, the organization changed its name to Turn Toward Peace. In 1967, a group split off to become the World Without War Council.
Scope and Contents note
The World Without War Council records contain minutes, resolutions, correspondence, memoranda, reports, financial records, serial issues, bulletins, newsletters, other printed matter, and audiovisual materials related to peace movements in the United States, pacifism, conscientious objectors, disarmament, nuclear weapons, American foreign policy, world affairs, and the Vietnam War.
The World Without War Council was a United States organization committed to ending war. In a statement of their goals and principles, the Council wrote, "Conflict is the nature of things; war, as a means of resolving conflict, is not. We will never rid the world of personal and small-group violence, but we can end the organized mass violence of war." ("Clarifying the Council's Work," Box 510). The Council envisioned the United States as an international leader in the work to end war and championed an interventionist strategy. Unlike many peace organizations, the Council rejected solutions that focused only on the reduction of United States military power. They believed that democratic policies were a requisite for peace and that international agreement would be needed to bring about the end of organized violence.
The WWWC had regional offices in Berkeley, New York, Chicago, and Seattle. As part of their mission, they assisted volunteer organizations and NGOs with developing their own programs, and created guidelines for other peace groups. The WWWC consulted for a variety of peace, education, labor, and religious organizations, such as the National Council on Philanthropy and the AFL-CIO. Meeting minutes, correspondence, and administrative files documenting their work can be found throughout the collection, often under the heading of "Office file" or "Chronological file."
The WWWC implemented many programs geared toward creating peace. Since the collection has not been arranged, the Index to WWWC Programs can serve as a guide to these materials. Although this index highlights large groupings of documents pertaining to specific programs, other program materials can be found throughout the collection.
The collection includes papers of Robert Pickus, founder of Acts of Peace and president of the WWWC. The Robert Pickus File (Box 509 to 520) includes correspondence, biographical documents, and printed matter relating to his life and work.
As noted throughout the finding aid, some boxes have been removed from the collection due preservation issues or rehousing of materials.
Index to WWWC Programs
145, 349-351
Alliance for Education in Global and International Studies (AEGIS)
91, 104, 143, 144, 440, 441
American Initiatives Project
54, 231, 429-430, 444-446
Assessing the Public Effort for Peace
164
Bay Area Americans and World Affairs Fellows Program
77, 80, 82, 89, 153, 236, 355-356, 409-410
Conscience and War
8, 37, 91
Diablo Valley Peace Education Project
37, 57, 99
Diablo Valley School Project
15, 257, 262
Diocese of Oakland
37, 147, 152, 266
Diocese of California, Episcopal
20-21, 210, 226
East Bay Draft Information and Counseling Service
294-295, 381-391, 503
Good Global Governance
44, 61, 360-361, 406-408
Historians Project
2, 12, 31, 35, 128, 455-456, 474-475, 478-479, 486
Immigrants and Citizenship Project (Common Good)
22-23, 33, 140, 164, 240
Improving American Competence in World Affairs
9, 27, 100, 127, 164, 208, 243, 413-414
International Conflict and American Organizations Project
6, 127, 154, 158, 161, 190, 223
National Council on Philanthropy
33-35, 54
Organizational Map Project
28, 243
Peace Ballot and Peace Platform
28, 100, 104
Peace and Elections
184, 195, 251
Project South Africa
411-412
Religious Leadership
56, 157, 164, 209
State Department/Independent Sector Project
132
Television Project
91, 132, 231, 243
U.S. Foreign Policy
44, 143, 198, 206
U.S. Response to the Arms Race
18, 85
VISA
91, 206, 243
Voluntary Organizations and a World Without War
World without War Council.; Disarmament.; Pacifism.; Peace.; United States--Foreign relations--1945-1989.; United States--Foreign relations.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; World politics--1945-1989.
- Acts for Peace, treasurer reports and ledger, 1958-1962 (Box 1)
- Turn Toward Peace, checks, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
- South Berkeley Community Church Peace Education Fund, balance sheet (Box 1)
- Commonwealth Club of California, 1975 (Box 3)
- Immigrants and Citizenship Program
  Scope and Contents note
  A project with the goals of strengthening common civic culture in the United States, clarifying debates around multiculturalism and diversity, and helping civic and educational organizations develop their own programs for promoting diversity and ideas of the common good, especially in the California Bay Area. The program was also referred to as the Common Good Project.
- Seafirst Bank Program, 1980 (Box 3)
- Midwest Conference on United Nations Reform, 1979 (Box 3)
- Business and international education, 1977 (Box 3)
- SALT II, 1979 (Box 3)
- Printed matter and writings by others, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  Includes letters of Robert Pickus, Alan Cranston, and Robert Woito
- Leaflets, 1978 (Box 4)
- Conferences and workshops (Box 4)
  - Amnesty World Without War Seminar, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Gandhi’s Relevance Today, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Shalom Workshop, 1977 (Box 4)
- Atomic Bomb Casualty Committee, 1966-1967 (Box 4)
- War Resisters League (Box 4)
- Printed matter and writings by others, 1960-1979 (Box 4)
- Jewish organizations, correspondence and program materials, 1953-1969 (Box 5)
  Includes Union of American Hebrew Congregations materials
- Printed matter and writings by others, 1972-1988 (Box 6)
- Foundation International Group, 1981 (Box 6)
- National Council on Philanthropy (Box 6)
- Correspondence, Robert Pickus, 1975-1981 (Box 6)
- Meeting materials, 1988 (Box 6)
- Christian organizations, correspondence and printed matter, 1970-1972 (Box 7)
  Includes Episcopal Diocese of Oakland, American Baptist Churches of the West, and Trinity Parish
- Campus protest, 1971 (Box 7)
- Diablo Valley Education Project, 1961-1970 (Box 8)
- "Teaching About Democratic Values and the Prevention of War and Disobedience,", 1968 (Box 8)
- Conferences, 1974-1976 (Box 9)
- Correspondence, Robert Pickus and Nancy Starr, 1973-1974 (Box 9)
- Office file, 1973-1974 (Box 9)
- "I'm Introducing Myself to All of You," Tim Zimmer, 1973 (Box 9)
- International Conflict and American Organizations (ICAO), 1974 (Box 9)
- Printed matter related to the CIA, Panama Canal, Federal Arts Program, and hunger, 1966-1980 (Box 10)
- Board meeting agenda, 1988 (Box 11)
- Correspondence, Robert Pickus, 1981 (Box 11)
- Northern California Consultative Group, 1985 (Box 11)
- "Brief Intro to a World Without War Council,", 1981 (Box 11)
- "Seven Roads to a World Without War" (Box 11)
- Printed matter related to South Africa, Latin America, religious organizations, and disarmament, 1979-1985 (Box 11)
- Immigrants and Citizenship Program, 1993-1995 (Box 12)
  - Reports, 1994-1995 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 12)
  - Meeting materials, 1994 (Box 12)
- "The All of It," speech, Robert Pickus, 1993 (Box 12)
- Non-Violent Action Against Nuclear Weapons, Lawrence Scott, 1957 (Box 13)
- Missle construction protests, 1958-1961 (Box 13)
- Wingspread Symposium, 1976 (Box 14)
- Hope for the Hungry, 1975 (Box 14)
- WWWC regional offices, 1967-1975 (Box 14)
  - Seattle, 1975 (Box 14)
  - New York, 1967-1972 (Box 14)
  - Midwest, 1970-1971 (Box 14)
- National Federation of Priests' Councils, correspondence, reports, printed matter, 1974-1975 (Box 15)
- Diocese of Oakland, 1961-1973 (Box 15)
- WWWC Issues Center, 1975-1976 (Box 15)
- National Catholic Education Association, correspondence, reports, conference materials, and printed matter, 1973-1976 (Box 16)
- Printed matter, Vietnam and Cambodia, 1965-1975 (Box 17)
- VISA Project, 1986-1989 (Box 18)
  Project of the WWWC of Northern California. Includes materials related to travel between United States and the Soviet Union.
- Pickus travel files, office files, and correspondence, 1972-1978 (Box 19)
- New York office files, 1972-1973 (Box 19)
- Draft and immigration to Canada, 1969-1971 (Box 20-21)
- East Bay Draft Information and Counseling Center, 1968-1972 (Box 20-21)
- WWWC programs
  - Vietnam and the Opinion-Makers, 1981 (Box 22)
  - Improving American Competence in World Affairs, 1979-1984 (Box 22-23)
- Conferences, 1979-1987 (Box 24)
- Speech, Paul Warnke, "SALT and the Test Ban,", 1977 (Box 24)
- "American and World Affairs: A Directory for Northern California," correspondence, promotional material, reports, 1981 (Box 24)
- Turn Toward Peace, correspondence, reports, meeting minutes, regional consultants file, 1961-1965 (Box 25)
  Includes material from Berkeley office
- Futures Committee Report, 1968 (Box 25)
- Conferences and workshops, 1962-1966 (Box 25)
  - War Resisters International, 1962 (Box 25)
  - Second National Convocation on the Challenge of Building Peace, 1970 (Box 25)
  - Mary Temple for Conference on Voluntary Organizations and a World Without War, 1966 (Box 25)
  - Exchange Network Conference, 1965 (Box 25)
- Correspondence, 1975- 1976 (Box 26)
- Office files for Berkeley and New York offices, 1972-1976 (Box 26)
- International Conflict and American Organizations (ICAO), 1975 (Box 27)
- Internship file, 1970-1975 (Box 27)
- WWWC national brochure, 1975 (Box 27)
- Correspondence, 1975 (Box 27)
- Peace and Elections program, correspondence and promotional materials, 1972 (Box 28)
- Peace Ballot and Peace Platform, 1975-1976 (Box 28)
- Strength Through Wisdom: A Critique of U.S. Capability project, 1980 (Box 29)
  Response to President Carter's commission report on improving United States competence in world affairs
- Turn Toward Peace, Pacific Regional Office, financial records, 1965-1966 (Box 30)
- Immigrant and Citizenship Program file, correspondence, grants, and program materials, 1993 (Box 31)
- California Council for the Humanities, 1978-1983 (Box 31)
- WWWC introductory materials, 1990-1992 (Box 31)
  Includes materials from board meetings and financial information
- WWWC programs
  - Improving American Competence in World Affairs, 1997 (Box 33)
  - Organizational Map Project, 1995-1998 (Box 33-35)
    Includes correspondence of Brian Brennan, reports, grants, and meeting materials
  - Immigrants and Citizenship Program, correspondence and printed matter, 1993-1998 (Box 35)
- Financial records, Acts for Peace and Turn Toward Peace, 1958-1964 (Box 36)
- Turn Toward Peace, Pacific Regional Office, 1967-1968 (Box 37)
- Diablo Valley Peace Center, 1964 (Box 37)
- Diablo Valley Schools Project, 1964-1975 (Box 37)
- Diocese of California, World Without War Program, 1971-1974 (Box 38)
  Includes material related to Catholic Diocese of Oakland
- Religious education, 1971-1975 (Box 38)
  Includes material related to American Friends Service Committee
- Correspondence, 1972-1975 (Box 39)
- Correspondence, KPFA (Pacifica Radio), Leonard Kenworthy (Box 40)
- World Without War publications program, 1968-1972 (Box 40)
- Office file, 1992-1994 (Box 41)
  - Board meetings, 1992-1994 (Box 41)
  - State of the Council, David Keck, 1994 (Box 41)
- Organizations (Box 42-43)
  - American Friends Service Committee, 1975-1995 (Box 42)
  - Aspen Institute booklets, 1990-1996 (Box 42)
  - ASPECT (Box 42)
  - American University, Peace and Conflict Resolution Seminar, brochure (Box 42)
  - American-Soviet Homestays, Inc. (Box 42)
  - American-Soviet Friendship Society (Box 42)
  - The American Prospect, 1992 (Box 42)
  - American Near East Refugee Aid (ANERA), 1986 (Box 42)
  - American Institute for Free Labor Development, 1998 (Box 42)
  - Amnesty International, 1991 (Box 42)
  - Asia Resource Center (Box 42)
  - Aquarian Research Foundation (Box 42)
  - Armenian General Benevolent Union (Box 42)
  - Asian Americans/Pacific Islanders in Philanthropy, 1993 (Box 42)
  - Asia Foundation (Box 42)
  - Friends Committee on National Legislation, 1977-1990 (Box 43)
  - Friends of Tibet, 1990 (Box 43)
  - Friends World Committee of Consultation, Report of the Americas, 1991 (Box 43)
  - Fulbright Association (Box 43)
  - The Fund for Peace (Box 43)
  - Fund for the Feminist Majority (Box 43)
  - Global File Monitor, Global Peace Studies, Global Connection, 1992 (Box 43)
  - Gandhi Peace Foundation (Box 43)
  - General Association of Korean Residents in Japan (Box 43)
  - Georgetown University, Center for Strategic and International Studies (Box 43)
  - Gandhi Institute for Non-Violence (Box 43)
  - Global Education Associates (Box 43)
  - ASCD, Global Education Network, Global Connections (Box 43)
  - Global Exchange, San Francisco (Box 43)
  - Global Family (Box 43)
  - Global File, Monitor (Box 43)
  - Global Forum on Spiritual and Parliamentary Leaders of Human Survival, New York (Box 43)
  - Global Fund for Women (Box 43)
  - Global Outlook (Box 43)
  - Global Tomorrow Coalition (Box 43)
  - Global Unity (Box 43)
  - Peace Education Foundation (Box 43)
  - Grassroots Peace Directory (Box 43)
  - Green Calendar for Social Change, 1988 (Box 43)
  - Green Library (Box 43)
  - Greenpeace (Box 43)
  - Humanity Guild (Box 43)
  - Habitat for Humanity (Box 43)
  - The Harriman Institute Forum (Box 43)
- Debate about Kahanism in Israeli Society, Gerald Cromer, 1984-1988 (Box 43)
- U. S. Response to the Arms Race, WWWC program, 1977 (Box 44)
- Office file, 1974-1984 (Box 44)
  - WWWC programs, Historians Project, 1978-1984 (Box 44)
  - Meetings, 1974-1979 (Box 44)
  - Internships, 1976 (Box 44)
  - New York Office files, personnel, funding, meetings, 1975-1976 (Box 44)
- Printed matter, education and African Peace Research Institute, 1989-1995, undated (Box 45)
- WWWC newsletters, Seattle and Portland, 1972 (Box 46)
- WWWC programs with religious organizations, 1968-1972 (Box 46-47)
- World Peace Brigade, 1963 (Box 48)
- Turn Toward Peace, 1962-1963 (Box 49)
- Speeches and writings, Robert Pickus, 1957-1968 (Box 50)
- Turn Toward Peace, meeting minutes, budget, correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 50)
- Poster for Robert Pickus signed by office staff, undated (Box 50)
- Organizations (Box 51)
  - San Francisco Theological Seminary, introductory materials (Box 51)
  - Thinkpeace, 1987 (Box 51)
    San Francisco study group for peace and disarmament
  - Sane/Freeze, 1989 (Box 51)
  - Saybrook Society, 1989 (Box 51)
  - Search for Common Ground, 1989 (Box 51)
  - Harvard University, program on nonviolent sanctions, Gene Sharp, 1984-1985 (Box 51)
  - A. Philip Randolph Institute (Box 51)
  - Professors World Peace Academy, 1988 (Box 51)
  - Public Agenda Foundation (Box 51)
  - Puebla Institute (Box 51)
  - Quaker United Nations Office, 1997 (Box 51)
  - Quest for Peace, Humanitarian Aid to Nicaragua (Box 51)
  - Research Institute on Communist Affairs, 1973-1974 (Box 51)
  - Rainforest Action Network (Box 51)
  - Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty, 1993 (Box 51)
  - Redefining Progress, San Francisco (Box 51)
  - Religion and Public Life (Box 51)
  - Pendle Hill, Quaker Study Center (Box 51)
  - Research Center for Religion and Human Rights in Closed Societies, 1988 (Box 51)
  - Refuse and Resist, New York (Box 51)
  - Resource Center for Nonviolence, Santa Cruz, CA (Box 51)
  - Resource Center for Women, Palo Alto, CA (Box 51)
  - Restoring the Earth, Berkeley, CA (Box 51)
  - Rockford Institute, Rockford, IL (Box 51)
  - Rutherford Institute, Charlotteville, VA (Box 51)
  - State of the World Forum (Box 51)
  - Witness for Peace (Box 51)
  - San Francisco Greens, 1988 (Box 51)
  - San Francisco Teleport (Box 51)
- Holt Ruffin, 1985-1990 (Box 52)
- WWWC Seattle newsletter, 1989 (Box 52)
- Jewish organizations, 1960-1968 (Box 53)
  Includes Union of American Hebrew Congregations correspondence and materials related to Temple Beth Am, Rabbi Joseph Glaser, and Rabbi Norman Hirsh
- WWWC programs
  - Improving the Public Dialogue on Peace and Security on Campus, 1985 (Box 54)
  - Assessing the Public Effort for Peace in America, 1974-1988 (Box 54)
  - Project Democracy (Box 54)
  - Organizational Map Project, circa 1990 (Box 54)
- James Madison Foundation, annual meeting, 1993 (Box 54)
- Northern California Consultative Group on Americans and World Affairs, meetings and internships, 1983-1993 (Box 54)
- National Association of Evangelicals, 1986 (Box 54)
- Office file, 1979-1988 (Box 55)
  - Board meetings, 1988 (Box 55)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1987 (Box 55)
  - Mission statement, 1987 (Box 55)
  - Reports, 1986-1987 (Box 55)
- Speech, George Weigel (Box 55)
- Correspondence, George Koros, Jerry Berlin, Mary Faulkner, Albert Shanker, American Federation of Teachers (Box 56)
- State Department/Independent Sector Project, Gordon Feller (Box 56)
- Brochures for foundations (Box 56)
- Vietnam, 1970 (Box 57)
- Leaflets (Box 57)
- Diablo Valley Schools Project, correspondence and clippings, 1967 (Box 57)
- REMOVED FROM COLLECTION (Box 58)
- United States Institute of Peace in Iowa, Second Annual Conference, 1986 (Box 59)
- American Voluntary Organizations, 1970-1973 (Box 59)
- Robert Pickus reports, 1969-1973 (Box 59)
  Includes reflection on eleven years of work at Berkeley
- "Next Steps to Open a New York Office,", 1973 (Box 59)
- Correspondence, 1973 (Box 59)
  Includes letters to or from Lois Barton, Arthur Hoppe, San Francisco Chronicle, Charles Beitz, Colgate University, Art Springer, Foster Parmelee, and Newletter, Society for Citizen Education in World Affairs, and Lillian Genser.
- Acts for Peace, survey report, 1956 (Box 59)
- Printed matter, 1955-1991 (Box 59)
  Includes War Resisters League magazine
- Vietnam reports and clippings, 1963-1969 (Box 60)
  Includes Turn Toward Peace education and action guide
- American Friends Service Committee, Peace Steering Committee, meeting minutes, 1960 (Box 61)
- Multicultural Initiative, 1994 (Box 61)
- WWWC Programs (Box 61)
  - Historian's Project, precis (Box 61)
  - Peace Intern Program, Seattle, 1973 (Box 61)
- Writings (Box 61)
  - Pluralizing the Soviet Union, George Weigel, 1983 (Box 61)
  - From Chaos to Conviction, George Weigel (Box 61)
  - Reflections on the Freeze, Robert Pickus (Box 61)
- Citizen Organization and the Foreign Policy Process, Democratic Engagement for a World in Crisis Conference, 1968 (Box 61)
- Correspondence, Carl Landauer (Box 61)
- Leaflets, 1962-1972 (Box 61)
- Regional offices, 1974-1994 (Box 62)
  - Seattle, 1976-1977 (Box 62)
  - New York, 1978-1981 (Box 62)
  - Chicago, 1974-1994 (Box 62)
- Vietnam peace proposals, 1967-1968 (Box 63)
- Institute for World Order, printed matter, 1974-1975 (Box 64)
- World Federalist Education Fund, printed matter, 1974 (Box 64)
- Conferences and workshops, 1974-1975 (Box 64)
- Board meetings, 1988-1989 (Box 65)
- Acts for Peace, correspondence and printed matter, 1958-1961 (Box 66)
- Program file, 1969-1972 (Box 67)
  Includes Seattle Intern Program and World Without War Council Speaker's Bureau
- Vietnamese Buddhist Peace Delegation, 1970-1973 (Box 68)
- WWWC executive committee meeting, intern program, and conferences, 1976-1979 (Box 68)
- Vietnam clippings and WWWC statements, 1965-1973 (Box 69-70)
- Peace in the Middle East program, research, 1973-1975 (Box 71)
- SANE policy statements and internal dispute (Box 72)
- Turn Toward Peace, "Building a Genuine International Peace Community,", 1963 (Box 72)
- Committee for Review of Our China Policy, 1963 (Box 72)
- "A Report on Vietnam and Congressional Candidates Interviews," Robert Pickus, 1966 (Box 72)
- International Rescue Committee, Emergency Assistance for Children and Refugees of Vietnam, 1967 (Box 72)
- Board meetings, 1987-1994 (Box 73-76)
  Includes materials from regional board meetings and the National Executive Board
- Conscience and War program, 1967-1970 (Box 77)
- Turn Toward Peace, Vietnam kit and working materials, 1964-1966 (Box 78)
- Foundations (Box 79)
  - Bydale Foundation, American Initiatives Project (Box 79)
  - Joyce Mertz-Gilmore Foundation, 1985 (Box 79)
  - Careth Foundation, 1984 (Box 79)
  - Carnegie Endowment and Carnegie Corporation (Box 79)
  - Chase Fund, 1981 (Box 79)
  - Airlie Foundation (Box 79)
  - Connecticut Humanities Council, 1975-1976 (Box 79)
  - Compton Foundation, 1987 (Box 79)
  - Cunningham & Walsh, Inc. (Box 79)
  - Archibald Charitable Foundation, 1987 (Box 79)
  - Boeing Corporation, 1979 (Box 79)
  - Gates Foundation, 1997 (Box 79)
  - Henry Jackson Foundation, 1992 (Box 79)
  - Safeco Insurance Co., 1982 (Box 79)
  - Seattle Seafirst, 1982 (Box 79)
  - Weyerhaeuser Foundation, 1981 (Box 79)
- Conscience and War program, 1990 (Box 80)
- Conscientious objectors and the draft, 1980-1990 (Box 80)
- WWWC newsletters (Box 81)
  - Portland, 1968-1986 (Box 81)
  - Seattle, 1970, 1975 (Box 81)
  - Midwest (Box 81)
  - Eugene, Oregon (Box 81)
- Conscience and War program, 1980-1990 (Box 82)
- Printed matter, Vietnam, 1973-1990 (Box 83)
- Turn Toward Peace, by-laws and materials from founding, 1961-1962 (Box 84)
- Vietnam kit (Box 84)
- WWWC kit, 1964 (Box 84)
- "The Challenge of Building Peace," Fund for Peace, Second Annual Convocation, 1970 (Box 84)
- Correspondence, New York office, 1975-1980 (Box 85)
- Foundations (Box 85)
  - Randolph Foundation (Box 85)
  - Christopher Reynolds Foundation, 1952-1990 (Box 85)
  - Schultz Foundation (Box 85)
- VISA Project, 1987-1991 (Box 86)
- Grant requests, National Endowment for the Humanities, 1978, 1995-1997 (Box 86)
- Newsletters, 1971 (Box 87)
  - Perspective, editor Anne Stadler, 1971 (Box 87)
  - At Work, WWWC New York newsletter, 1971 (Box 87)
- Foundations, correspondence and requests (Box 88)
  - Rockefeller Brothers Fund, 1984-1989 (Box 88)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1984 (Box 88)
  - Stern Fund, 1984 (Box 88)
  - Topstone Fund, 1977 (Box 88)
  - William C. Whtiner Foundation, 1975 (Box 88)
  - Union Pacific Foundation, 1981 (Box 88)
  - Pew Charitable Trusts, 1990 (Box 88)
- Fundraising and donations, 1977-1984 (Box 88)
- Conscience and War program, 1980-1991 (Box 89)